so to give you a little bit of a flavor
for how these things can can get a
little bit more complicated look at this
statement here so we're going to have
not P or not q and I want to try to
figure out what does this mean it's
already getting a little bit complicated
of course I can keep on adding I could
add an r i could add more variables and
keep on combining these negations and
conjunctions and ores as much as I wish
so I want to have this systematic way of
doing it and we're going to use the
truth table here so let's pull up our
template
and you're notice that it's going to be
a little bit bigger than it was last
time so if I go way off to the left
again we're going to have the same sort
of beginning Parts here so I want to
have an initial input variable
p and another initial input Q so those
are my same two inputs that we've had
before and I can go down and fill out
the different possibilities that we have
exactly we've done before I could have
true and true I could have true and
false I could have false and true and I
could have false and false so the same
sort of beginning moves here now I don't
want to jump right to the final column
over here I don't want to jump right to
this final answer I want to give some
intermediate ones that are going to help
me along so what I'm going to do in
these ones is I'm going to put not P
here and I'm going to put not Q over
there and I'm going to try to figure out
what those are and then find finally
after I'm done with everything I can
come down here and I can come and put
this inside of
there all right so not p is just exactly
the opposite of whatever p is if if p is
going to be true then not p is going to
be false p is true not p is false p is
false not p is true and P is false not p
is true all right so I'm able to fill
that in pretty easily same with not Q
not Q I just look at Q q and then I take
the negation of every one so if Q is
true then not Q is going to be false
false is going to turn into a true true
is going to turn into a false and false
is going to turn into a
true so now comes the tricky part I want
to put these two things together because
I have that it's going to be not P or
not q and so that tells me if one of the
two of these columns the not p and the
not Q columns is true then my output is
going to be true as well so what do I
have here I have a false and a false so
neither of them is true it's not the
case that one or the other one is going
to be so neither of them is true and so
therefore it is going to be
false down here one of the two is true
this one's true so one or the other is
true yeah that works that's going to be
a
true true and false one or the other
that's going to be another true and true
and true one of them is going to be true
in fact both of them true and so that's
going to be a final true so what do I
get false true true and true so these
truth tables are very useful at taking
these complicated compounded logical
statements and just trying to interpret
when are they false and when are they
true depending on the initial parameters
the P's and the q's